Guide to the Hispanic Communities Documentation Project records and oral histories ARC.032
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 1: Publicized oral histories, 1988-1989
  - Pascualy, Jose, 1988 August 25; 1989.004.05
    José Pascualy, affectionately known as Monchito, was born in Mayagüez, Puerto Rico, and moved with his mother and four siblings to El Barrio-- or the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan--when he was a child. He later moved to the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, where he owned and operated a flower and party services business. His wife owned a bakery in Sunset Park. Pascualy was active in his community; participating in civic groups such as Los Pioneros and the Fifth Avenue Merchants Association.
    In this interview, Jose "Monchito" Pascualy recounts his childhood in Manhattan's El Barrio and his adult life in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. He discusses the history of the Puerto Rican community and the civic group Los Pioneros. Pascualy describes several Latino/a and Puerto Rican parades such as the Pioneers Parade, the Puerto Rican Day Parade, and the Hispanic Parade. He also mentions resistance to the organization of subsequent Puerto Rican or Latino/a parades from Sunset Park's local officials. He discusses generational differences between Puerto Ricans and highlights some Puerto Rican cultural traits. Pascualy also talks about immigration of other Latino/a nationalities as well as the growth of the Chinese American community in the area. He elaborates on the theme of gentrification of Sunset Park and the effect on its residents, especially those of limited means. He discusses the efforts made by merchant members of the Fifth Avenue Merchants Association to improve the neighborhood by bringing in more commerce to Sunset Park's Fifth Avenue. Interview in Spanish conducted by Morton Marks.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Race relations -- United States
  - Falcon, Pablo, 1989 May 1; 1989.004.06
    Pablo Falcón was born in Bayamón, Puerto Rico and moved to the neighborhood of Santurce at ten years old. After having spent three years stationed in Panama with the United States Army during World War II, he relocated to the Bronx, New York as his family had already moved there. He spent nineteen years living in the Bronx, working at an electronics company, and later moved to the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn to work as a building superintendent. Falcón was a toy-maker since childhood; using his father's carpentry tools and materials to make toys for himself and his friends. He decided to showcase traditional Puerto Rican toys at a Three Kings Day celebration in Brooklyn and since then his craft gained enough popularity to be showcased in several venues such as El Museo del Barrio and the television show "Sábado Gigante." Falcón was an active member of the group Los Hijos e Hijas de María and the Guardian Angels Church on Ocean Parkway in Brooklyn.
    In this interview, Pablo Falcón talks about growing up in Bayamón, Puerto Rico. He narrates how he started making toys using his father's tools and materials as well as scraps he found around the house. Falcón also narrates how his toys gained popularity in the United States and how nostalgia played a role in this. He also compares the materials used in the construction of the toys in Puerto Rico and the materials he used in New York. He briefly discusses the ethnic composition of the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn, his various employments, and the charitable activities of the church group Los Hijos e Hijas de María. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Hernán.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Rico; Santurce (San Juan, P.R.); Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Toy making
  - Diaz, Carmen, 1988 September 8; 1989.004.07
    Carmen Diaz was born in Guaynabo, Puerto Rico, to a restaurant-owning family. She was one of five children. Diaz lived in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn from 1970 up to the time of the 1988 interview. She became an active member of the community, and became involved with La Liga de Damas Unidas de Brooklyn (League of United Women of Brooklyn). Founded by Jose "Monchito" Pascualy, this organization worked toward the development of the Latino communities throughout the borough of Brooklyn.
    Carmen Diaz relates anecdotes about her grandmother, a spiritual healer with a wide knowledge of medicinal plants and discusses details of plants and their use in curing various ailments. There is also a discussion of belief in witches in her hometown. Diaz also supplies a wealth of detail about folklore connected with the observance of El Día de San Juan, or Midsummer Day. She discusses some of the "pioneer" Puerto Rican women leaders in Sunset Park. During her many years in the neighborhood, she has seen Sunset Park undergo many changes. As she puts it, it has gone from an "American" barrio to a Hispanic enclave. The community's growth occurred so rapidly that many Latino/a children have had to be sent to schools outside of Sunset Park. Diaz discusses the ethnic composition of the neighborhood in the last part of the interview. Interview in Spanish conducted by Morton Marks.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Rico; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Dinners and dining |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medicinal plants; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York Region |x Religion; Spiritual healing and spiritualism; Storefronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Alianza de damas unidas de Brooklyn
  - Hernandez, Ismael, 1989 May 4; 1989.004.08
    Ismael Hernandez was born circa 1970 in Quebradillas, a small town in the west of Puerto Rico. Hernandez came to New York as an infant where he attended school until the third grade, and then returned to Puerto Rico for six years. He came back to New York in 1985 at the age of 15 and lived with an older brother in the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn. His parents remained in Puerto Rico.
    In the interview, Hernandez discusses his Latino/a friends, as well as relations between African-American and Latino/a students at Bushwick High School, where he is a student. He talks about his experiences in the school's bilingual program, and about life in the neighborhood. He mentions Casa Borínquen, a local Latin dance club, and ''La Avenida de Puerto Rico," or Graham Avenue, so called because of the large number of Latino/a businesses there. Finally, he talks of his hopes of returning to Puerto Rico and continuing his education there, and of the impact American culture has had on him. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; African Americans |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dominican Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ecuadorian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; High school students |z New York (State) |z New York; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Rican youth; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century
  - Wilson, Alonso, 1988 August 11; 1989.004.09
    Alonso Wilson de Briano was born in 1930s Panama and became interested in music at an early age, due to the influence of his father, a choir master. Wilson attended the Conservatory of Music of Panama and then continued his studies at the National Institute of Panama. He wrote a number of musical compositions that received recognition, and was a member of the Cleff Melodiers, an all-male choral group that performed American spirituals. Wilson came to the United States seeking economic betterment and success in his musical career. In the mid-1950s, he lived briefly in Manhattan and in Roosevelt, Long Island, but when the rest of his family arrived they settled in Brooklyn. In 1958 he performed with a quintet called "Windsor Club" at the Carnegie Recital Hall in a program called "Modern Expressions in the Music of Panama.'' He then formed a Latin band and continued to perform with different groups in the Bronx. Following his graduation from Brooklyn College, he attempted to return to Panama but employment conditions forced him to return to New York. Wilson lived in Long Island in 1988, where he taught music in a local high school.
    In the interview, Alonso Wilson de Briano weaves high points of his personal journey and professional development with reverence for songwriters and musicians. The music that Wilson developed is known as Windsor style, and it combines Afro-Panamanian, Cuban, and West Indian musical elements. It sounds like a blend of mambo and calypso, and it was the popular music of Panamanian-West Indians arriving in Brooklyn in the 1950s. In Wilson's own words, Panama is a country ''with a foot in each side;" one coming from the Latino/a side and the other from the English-speaking West Indies. Wilson feels that Panamanian-West Indian culture is becoming more and more Latinized, both in Brooklyn and in Panama. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.
    Access is available onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cuba; Panama; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Calypso (Music) |z New York (State) |z New York; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Composition (Music); English as a second language; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians; Panamanian Americans; Popular music |x Writing and publishing |z New York (State) |z New York; West Indian Americans
  - Samuel, Anesta, 1988 August 16; 1989.004.10
    S. Anesta Samuel is one of the founders of the Dedicators, a club organized in 1953 with the aim of raising money for scholarships in the United States and in Panama. The organization is also devoted to the preservation of Panamanian-West Indian culture. Samuel was born circa 1919 in Panama to a couple who migrated from the West Indian island of Montserrat. Her father came to work in the Canal Zone, and she grew up in an all-West Indian settlement called Red Tank. While still a child, she resolved never to work for the Canal Zone government because of their discriminatory policies toward West Indians. There were also limited educational possibilities for West Indians, with little or no advancement beyond the eighth grade. While still in her teens, Samuel opened a beauty shop in the town of La Boca, the largest settlement of West Indians in the Canal Zone. The business did well enough to enable Samuel to open another beauty shop and a beauty school. She married in 1937, and continued to do well financially. After World War II, her husband decided to come to New York to study, and she accompanied him.
    In the interview, S. Anesta Samuel relates notable moments of growing up in Panama and adapting to and thriving in new surroundings in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn for much of her life. Samuel discusses her efforts at sponsoring other Panamanian-West Indians who were coming to New York in search of opportunities. She describes the charitable work that she began with old friends, founding a club called Las Servidoras, which became a forerunner of The Dedicators, founded in 1953. Samuel considers the thinning out of distinctly Panamanian heritage in American life, and the efforts of the Panamanian-West Indian Heritage Association to preserve cultural elements. In closing, she acknowledges the generation gap between the Panama-born immigrants and Panamanian American youth. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Panama; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Balls (Parties) |z New York (State) |z New York; Beauty Shops; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Education; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Panamanian Americans; Race discrimination; Spanish language; West Indian Americans; Panamanian-West Indian Heritage Association
  - Russell, Carlos, 1988 August 10; 1989.004.11
    Dr. Carlos Russell was born in Panama. Dr. Russell grew up in the two Panamas; the West Indian one and the Latino/a one. His parents were separated, so he lived in Panama City with his mother and would travel to the ''West Indian'' city of Colón to see his father. He studied at the National Institute in Panama and attended the Episcopal Church. In 1955 Dr. Russell left Panama and went to Chicago. There, Dr. Russell got involved in politics in the Panamanian-West Indian community and also in the Black American community. Later, after having spent a number of years in Brooklyn, he was instrumental in arranging the National Conference of Panamanians in the Poconos, and is a founder of ''El Bahiano,'' the first Panamanian-West Indian newspaper to be published in both English and Spanish. As a Dean of the School of Contemporary Studies at Brooklyn College, he along with others began to promote cultural activities and to participate more in Panamanian politics both here and in Panama. In 1988, he resided in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In the interview, Dr. Carlos Russell recalls that he and his family were in the "diaspora'' of Panamanian-West Indians. His grandparents came from Barbados and Jamaica, and other relatives came from some of the French West Indies. He opines that in Panama many of the West Indians who spoke English in the past have now turned to Spanish because English speakers were looked down upon. In the seventies and eighties, however, things changed and some Panamanians of West Indian descent have been appointed to government positions. Dr. Russell thinks that most of the youngsters who come to the United States from Panama in 1988 are not as ambitious as his generation, and the few who are politically active identify more with Latin America than with the West Indies. This attitude is prevalent in Panama as well, where there is a major Latinization among the West Indian descended communities. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.
    Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Education; English as a second language; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Panamanian Americans; Political participation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race discrimination; West Indian Americans
  - Fisher, Sylvia, 1988 August 20; 1989.004.12
    Sylvia Fisher, in the United States as an adult since 1962, is originally from Panama. She is of West Indian descent. In 1988, she was a resident of the East Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn and was an active participant in two dance clubs; Cornelia and Friendship Square Social. She married in Panama and raised three children in Brooklyn. Fisher was previously employed with two banks and performed accounting duties for a garment district business in Manhattan at time of this 1988 interview.
    In the interview, Sylvia Fisher elaborates on her experiences as a child in Panama. She mentions the Canal Zone and the schools that she attended there. Fisher discusses her early involvement with square dancing and its relationship with her Panamanian West Indian identity. She talks about the evolution of square dancing in Panama. She mentions some similarities as well as differences in the music and style of square dancing as it was known in Panama and the United States. She also cites examples of occasions where the square dancing club to which she belongs in Brooklyn, has performed. Fisher also references other Panamanian West Indian social clubs in Brooklyn that are trying to preserve this group's culture, particularly that of square dancing, and the difficulties these clubs are facing in their attempts to get young people interested in square dancing. Lastly, the narrator discusses her life in Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Panama; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Dancers |z New York (State) |z New York; English as a second language; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Panamanian Americans; Race discrimination; Societies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Square dancing; West Indian Americans
  - Kelly, Reynaldo, 1989 May 4; 1989.004.13
    Reynaldo Kelly was born in Colón, Panama in 1970. Although Colon was originally an English-speaking city, Kelly was primarily a Spanish speaker who was learning English as a second language. His friends in the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn were mostly Spanish-speaking, and his musical tastes were mostly Latin Caribbean.
    In the interview, Reynaldo Kelly discusses bilingualism in Panama, and bilingual classes at Bushwick High School, where he is a student. He talks about the changes he sees in his native city, which he visits every summer, and he also describes Carnival in Colón. He describes life in the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn and his plans for future studies. He looks forward to returning to Panama, where his father still lives. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Panama; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Carnival; English as a second language; High school students |z New York (State) |z New York |x Conduct of life; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; International cooking; Panamanian Americans; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; West Indian Americans
  - Perez, Gerardo, 1989 February 3; 1989.004.14
    Gerardo Perez, alias ''El Viejo Yayo," is originally from Guanabacoa, Cuba. When this 1989 interview occurred, he had lived in Brooklyn for twenty-four years with his wife, daughter, son-in-law and grandson. A restaurant entrepreneur by nature, Perez had spent most of his life working in restaurants.
    In the interview, Gerardo Perez discusses his family's business in Cuba as well as in the States. He details in depth how he started his present restaurant, El Viejo Yayo. As Perez tells his story, he provides some insight into the effects of the Communist Revolution on his family and, to some extent, on the country as a whole. In addition, the dilemma of national dislocation, sponsorship and immigration is highlighted. He talks about his journey through Spain and Costa Rica before arriving in Brooklyn. Perez recalls his difficulty with learning English as a second language. Throughout the interview, he also mentions some cultural customs that his family has brought over from Cuba, and still practice today. Perez sees other problems that are affecting quality of life in New York City, and particularly Brooklyn. Crime is his main concern. He elaborates on how drugs and the number of robberies have escalated in the past few years, and what the police force is doing about it. However, Perez provides some insight into how the various restoration projects, in the past as well as in the late 1980s, have helped make Brooklyn a livable, growing borough. Interview conducted by Lucia Rodriguez.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cuba; Miami (Fla.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cuban Americans; Dinners and dining |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Language and languages; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Gomez, Olga, 1989 February 28; 1989.004.15
    Olga Gomez, married and the mother of two children, is originally from Cuba. A longtime resident of the borough when the interview occurred in 1989, Gomez lived first in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn and then in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    Olga Gomez begins the interview by giving details on Hispanics in Brooklyn's history who can be classified as "pre-pioneers.'' She mentions a couple of Cubans who came in the early 1900s to Brooklyn to live, work, and study. She also talks about her political involvement in the Latino/a community. She elaborates on why she is a Republican and also shares her feelings about being a woman in politics. She gives her viewpoints on the topic of the Hispanic identity. In doing so she talks about Spanish heritage. She analyzes the educational opportunities of the Latino/a in the United States. Gomez looks at programs like bilingualism and special education in relation to the Latino/a student. She also comments on Latino/a organizations in Brooklyn, in addition to activities like parades that they sponsor. According to her, the Latino/a people in Brooklyn are moving forward; socially, economically, as well as politically. Interview in Spanish conducted by Lucia Rodriguez.
  - Gaston, Mariana, 1988 December 15; 1989.004.16
    Mariana Gastón was born in Havana, Cuba in 1949 to a Cuban father and a Mexican mother. In 1961, after spending a year in Mexico, her family arrived in the United States. After living for fourteen years in different cities in southwestern Virginia, where her father taught architecture at various universities, she came to New York to study. Gastón is a graduate of Manhattanville College. At the time of the 1988 interview, she resided in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In this interview, Mariana Gastón draws on her experiences to provide insight into the development of relationships between Cubans living in Cuba and those living outside the country. She describes her role in the founding of a multicultural and multi-ethnic public school in Brooklyn, where she was also a teacher. She further discusses her involvement with two magazine publications that attempted to examine the historical process and aftermath of the revolution, as well as her participation in the Brigada Antonio Maceo. The publications sought to open the process of dialogue and reconciliation, while the Brigada was actively involved in the reunification of family members living in the United States and Cuba, and even sponsored a trip back to Cuba that is the subject of the documentary Fifty-five Hermanos. Gastón also reflects on the social and economic evolution of the different racial groups of Cubans in the United States. Additionally, she covers topics such as the early migration of Cubans to Brooklyn and the old Cuban community in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn; and the displacement of families due to gentrification. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.